Finding Aid for School of Nursing (University of Michigan) publications 1913-2010
Bentley Historical Library, University of Michigan
School of Nursing (University of Michigan) publications 1913-2010
University of Michigan. School of Nursing.
Includes bibliographies, pamphlets and brochures, bulletins and college catalogs, calendars, directories, histories, manuals, newsletters, programs, proposals, surveys, and school yearbooks. Also contains publications from Continuing Education Services, the Office of Development and Alumni Affairs, the Nursing History Society, the Centennial Celebration, and nursing student groups
9733 Bimu C261 2
7 linear feet
Bentley Historical Library University of Michigan
Publications are received periodically from the unit (Donor no. 6818 )
The School of Nursing Publications are open for research.
Professional nursing education began in the United States in 1873. By 1900 there were 432 schools of nursing operating nationwide. This national trend came to Ann Arbor in 1891 when the University of Michigan Training School for Nurses was organized. The nursing program was established by the Medical School, in large part so that qualified nurses could be found to staff a newly erected University Hospital building.
The connection between the hospital and the nursing program was recognized in 1912, when the school for nurses was reorganized and placed under the direct control of the University Hospital. In 1928 the program's official title was belatedly changed to University Hospital School of Nursing of the University of Michigan. In 1941 the Regents established the nursing program as an independent university teaching unit, the University of Michigan School of Nursing. Although recognized as independent, the school's senior administrative officer was not given the title of dean until 1955.
The original curriculum for the school consisted of a two-year, non-degree program. In 1902 the Regents extended the basic curriculum to three years. In 1915 the first full-time instructor was hired, and in 1919 a second, five-year program, leading to the conferring of a university degree was established. In 1944 it was agreed that the combined course in the liberal arts and nursing should be phased out, in favor of a new program, leading to a bachelor of science in nursing degree.
In 1952 the curriculum was radically revised. The three-year program was discontinued and replaced by a four-year program leading to a BSN. In 1961 the curriculum was expanded to include the school's first masters degree, in psychiatric nursing. The next year, 1962, a masters degree program in medical-surgical nursing was begun. The four-year program, as well as the two master degree programs, received full accreditation, through the National League for Nursing, in 1963. In 1967 the school once again extensively revised its curriculum, with the reforms being placed in effect in 1968. In 1967 the school also launched a major continuing education program for practicing nurses, funded through the Michigan Association for Regional Medical Programs. In the early 1970s the school expanded its degree programs by offering, for the first time, a research-based Ph.D. in Nursing.
At its founding the school was limited to a student body of eight. This number expanded gradually. In 1912 there were about 100 students. Entrance requirements established by the turn of the century specified that students must be women, between the ages of 22 and 32, of superior education and refinement. Specific educational achievements for admission were not imposed until 1915, when possession of a high school diploma was made mandatory. In 1926 it was agreed that incoming nursing students should meet the same admission criteria as students entering the College of Literature, Science and the Arts. It was also agreed, in 1926, that nursing students would receive their basic science instruction through the Medical School. Student comfort, and the nursing program's prestige, were both increased in 1923 with the announcement of a $600,000 gift from Senator James Couzens for the construction of a nurses residence, Couzens Hall. The school's capabilities were dramatically increased in 1958 with the opening of a separate building for the school of nursing, constructed as a part of the Medical Science I complex. By 1970 the school had approximately 1,000 students, one of the largest enrollments in the nation.
The tenure of Dean Rhetaugh Dumas (1981-1994), the school's first African-American dean, brought a number of organizational and curricular changes in the School of Nursing. The Center for Nursing Research was established in 1982 to serve as the central coordinating body for faculty research and to foster collaborative relationships with other units and institutions involved in related research. New programs were developed in Gerontological Nursing, Nurse-Midwifery, Occupational Health Nursing, and Home Health Care. Existing programs, including Nursing Administration, Psychiatric Mental Health Nursing, and the undergraduate studies curriculum, were completely revamped. In 1990, the school's once autonomous academic areas were realigned to form three academic divisions: the Division of Acute, Critical and Long-Term Care, which included Medical-Surgical Nursing and Psychiatric Mental Health Nursing; the Division of Health Promotion and Risk Reduction Programs, which included Community Health Nursing and Parent-Child Nursing; and the Division of Nursing Business and Health Systems Programs, which included Nursing Administration.
Diversity and increased visibility on the university campus were central priorities of the school during Dean Dumas' tenure. The Office of Minority Affairs (later renamed the Office of Multicultural Affairs) was established in the 1980s to focus on the recruitment and retention of students, faculty and staff of color. Dumas was highly active in university affairs, serving on a number of presidential and university task forces and committees related to health affairs and issues affecting women and people of color. This visibility enabled the school to request and receive university funding resources to a greater degree than ever before. After years of lobbying and planning, the School of Nursing moved into renovated space at 400 North Ingalls, part of the former St. Joseph's Hospital, in 1989, the first time in many years that the entire school had been housed together.
Deans of the School of Nursing
1891-1892 Jane Pettigrew
1892-1893 M.E. Davis
1893-1896 Alice Padfield
1896-1898 Anna Harrison
1898-1899 Amy Miller
1899-1901 Grace Ellsworth
1901-1903 Helen Balcom
1903-1906 Ida Tracy
1906-1909 Mary C. Haarer
1909-1910 Ann E. Whitley
1910-1911 Luella Bristol
1911-1913 Elizabeth Holt
1913-1915 Jane M. Pindell
1915-1918 Fantine C. Pemberton
1918-1922 Mary A. Welsh
1922-1923 Louise Gliem
1923-1925 Alice Lake
1925-1930 Shirley C. Titus
1930-1940 Marian Durell
1940-1972 Rhoda Russell
1972-1973 Norma E. Marshall (acting dean)
1973-1975 Carolyne K. Davis
1975-1976 Maxine Loomis (acting dean)
1976-1980 Mary Lohr
1981-1994 Rhetaugh G. Dumas
1994 - Ada S. Hinshaw
The Publications of the School of Nursing is divided into four series: Unit Publications, Sub-Unit Publications, Topical Files and Student Publications. Restricted files are directories which are closed for 10 years after the date of publication.
Subjects:
University of Michigan--Students--Social life and customs.; University of Michigan. School of Nursing.; Bibliographies.; Pamphlets.; Bulletins.; Calendars.; Directories.; Histories.; Newsletters.; Programs.; Proposals.; Student publications.; Yearbooks.
Genre/Form:
Bibliographies.; Pamphlets.; Bulletins.; Calendars.; Directories.; Histories.; Newsletters.; Programs.; Proposals.; Student publications.; Yearbooks.; Scalpel.; Artery
- Unit Publications
  Unit Publications include bulletins and a run of the newsletters Bulletin and News and Notes, as well as The Scalpel and Paragon, student yearbooks of the School of Nursing. Also included is a college history. Faculty, graduate student and student handbooks will be found under the heading "Manuals".
  - Abstracts
    - Abstract of Research by Clinical Nursing Specialists, 1965-1975 (Box 1)
    - Abstract of Research by Graduates of the Graduate Programs in Nursing, 1976-1982 (Box 1)
    - Abstracts of Research by Graduates of the Master's Degree Programs in Nursing, 1983-1988 (Box 1)
  - Addresses
    - State of the School, 1993 An Era of Tradition 1981-1993, 1993 (Box 1)
  - Bibliographies
    - Faculty and Ph.D. Student Publications, 1973-1983 (Box 1)
  - Brochures
    - School of Nursing
      - 1952-1992 (Box 1)
    - Community Based Bachelor of Science in Nursing Degree for Registered Nurses, 1975-1976 (Box 1)
    - Conferences
      - Miscellaneous 1963-1990 (Box 1)
    - Course Listings 1969-1973 (Box 1)
    - 4 Year Basic Professional Program in Nursing, [1952]-1968 (Box 1)
    - The Friends Scholars Program, undated (Box 1)
    - Graduate Programs
      - Miscellaneous 1962-1990 (Box 1)
    - Homeopathic Hospital Training School for Nurses, undated (Box 1)
    - On Becoming a Nurse at the University of Michigan, 1948-1951 (Box 1)
  - Bulletins
    - College Catalogs
      - 1915-1995, 19 folders (Box 1)
      - 1996-1997 (Box 1)
      - 2003-2009, 6 folders (Box 1)
    - Graduate Programs (Box 2)
      - 1976-1989, 4 folders (Box 2)
  - Calendars
    - Common Calendar, 1983/84, 1994/95 (Box 2)
  - Directories
    - 1983-1984 (Box 2)
    - Faculty and Staff, 1971/72-1977/78 (Box 2)
    - Faculty and Staff Directory
      - 1984/85-1985/86 (Box 2)
      - 1995-1996 (Box 2)
    - Faculty Directory, 1982/83 (Box 2)
    - Faculty in Profile, 1992/93 (Box 2)
    - The 1993 University of Michigan School of Nursing Graduating Class, 1993 (Box 2)
  - Flyers 1988-1991 (Box 2)
  - Histories
    - A History of the University of Michigan School of Nursing, 1953 (Box 2)
  - Manuals
    - Clinical Simulation Laboratory Policies Manual, 1993 (Box 2)
    - Constitution, By-Laws--House Rules of the Nurses' Training School, undated (Box 2)
    - Doctoral Program Advisement Handbook, 1990 (Box 2)
    - Employment at University Hospital as a Nursing Assistant, 1964 (Box 2)
    - Faculty Handbook
      - 1956-1977, 8 folders (Box 2)
    - Faculty Handbook: Appointments, Promotions and Tenure, 1982 (Box 2)
    - Faculty Handbook: Personnel Policies and Procedures, 1989-1994 (Box 2)
    - Graduate Handbook, 1994/95-1995/96 (Box 7)
    - Graduate Student Handbook, 1978-1984 (Box 7)
    - Guide to Financial Aid for Graduate Nurses, 1981 (Box 7)
    - New Student Handbook, 1977-1978 (Box 7)
    - Procedure Script for University of Michigan School of Nursing Convocation, 1990 (Box 7)
    - Recruitment: Dynamics and Direction, 1984 (Box 7)
    - Rules for Pupil Nurses, undated (Box 7)
    - Student Handbook
      - 1938 (Box 7)
      - 1949 (Box 7)
      - 1977/78-1988/89 (Box 7)
      - 2007-2008 (Box 7)
    - Undergraduate Handbook, 1994/95-1995/96 (Box 7)
    - Undergraduate Academic Policy and Proceedures Handbook, 2006-2007 2009-2010, 2 folders (Box 7)
    - Master's Academic Policy and Proceedures Handbook, 2005-2007 2009-2010, 3 folders (Box 7)
    - Doctoral Academic Policy and Proceedures Handbook, 2005-2007 2009-2010, 3 folders (Box 7)
    - Academic Advising 1975 1976-1977 (Box 7)
  - Newsletters (Box 3)
    - Bulletin
      - volumes 1-14 1981-1995 (Box 3)
    - Care and Discovery
      [Supersedes News and Notes]
      - 1996-1998 undated (Box 3)
    - Community Health News
      - circa 1989 (Box 3)
    - The Dial
      - volume 2 1930 (Box 3)
    - Focus
      - 1974-1975 (Box 3)
    - News and Notes
      - 1986-1995, 4 folders (Box 3)
        (Precedes Care and Discovery)
    - Research Newsletter
      - volume 1-4 1978-1982 (Box 3)
    - Scalpel
      - 1923-1928, 6 folders (Box 4)
    - Senior Newsletter, 1991 (Box 4)
    - The University of Michigan School of Nursing Newsletter (Box 4)
    - 1972-1973 (Box 4)
  - Programs
    - Commencement 1913-1917 (Box 4)
    - Convocation 1980-1995 (Box 4)
    - Miscellaneous 1992 (Box 4)
  - Proposals
    - RN Studies Curriculum Proposal, 1990 (Box 4)
  - Reports
    - Progress Report
      - volume 1 1973 (Box 4)
      - Appendix A: Supplement to volume 2 1973 (Box 4)
    - Revision of Graduate Program in Medical-Surgical Nursing, 1986 (Box 4)
    - Self-Study Report for Continuing Accreditation by the National League for Nursing
      - volume 1 1985 (Box 4)
      - volume 2: Appendices 1985 (Box 4)
    - A Survey of Hospital Nurses: Summary Report, 1981 (Box 4)
  - Surveys
    - Faculty Research Interest Survey, 1980/81-1982/83 (Box 4)
    - Survey of Faculty Research, 1985/86-1991, 2 folders (Box 4)
  - Symposia
    - Faculty Research Symposium, 1983-1986 (Box 4)
    - Graduate Student Nursing Research Symposium
      - Brochures 1974-1988 (Box 4)
      - Programs 1977-1988 (Box 4)
    - National Nursing Symposia on Home Health Care
      - Abstracts 1985-1986 (Box 4)
      - Abstracts and Presentation Outlines 1987-1997 (Box 7)
      - Programs 1985-1993 (Box 4)
    - Nursing Research: Developing the Science of Caring, 1987 (Box 4)
  - Yearbooks
    - Paragon, 1991 (Box 4)
    - The Scalpel
      - 1924-1928, 1 volumes (Box 4)
      - 1929-1947, 11 volumes (Box 5)
- Sub-Unit Publications
  Sub-Unit Publications consist of materials produced by units within the School of Nursing, These include the Office of Development and Alumni Affairs, Continuing Education Services, the Graduate Program in Surgical Nursing, the North Campus Nursing Center, the Nursing History Society, the Office of Student Services, and Sigma Theta Tau.
  - Center for Nursing Research
    - Brochures undated (Box 5)
    - Faculty Research Activities Survey, 1983/84-1985/86 (Box 5)
  - Child/Adolescent Health Behavior Research Center
    - Brochures undated (Box 5)
  - Continuing Education Services
    - Bibliographies
      - Guide to Nursing Resource Materials: Inservice Education, Heart, Cancer and Stroke, circa 1971 (Box 5)
    - Development and Alumni Affairs, Office of (Box 5)
    - Honor Roll of Donors 1989 (Box 5)
  - Graduate Program in Surgical Nursing (Box 6)
    - Reports
      - Five Year Report 1968 (Box 6)
  - North Campus Nursing Center
    - Brochures undated (Box 6)
  - Nursing History Society
    - Brochures
      - The Nursing History Society of the University of Michigan, undated (Box 6)
  - Office of Student Affairs
    - Newsletters
      - The Integrator, 1995 (Box 6)
  - Sigma Theta Tau
    - Newsletters
      - Rho Chapter, 1987 (Box 6)
  - Space Planning Committee
    - Reports
      - Final Report of the Space Planning Committee of the School of Nursing, 1985 (Box 6)
- Topical Publications
  Topical Publications include materials relating to the Centennial Celebration and Martin Luther King Day activities.
  - Centennial Celebration
    - Brochures
      - Centennial Commemorative Brochure, 1991 (Box 6)
    - Calendars
      - The Nursing Centennial Calendar, 1991-1992 (Box 6)
    - Programs
      - A Second Century of Leadership, 1991 (Box 6)
  - Development
    - Brochures undated (Box 6)
  - Diamond Jubilee
    - Diamond Jubilee of Nursing Education at the University of Michigan, 1891-1966, 1966 (Box 6)
  - Martin Luther King Day
    - Invitations 1989 (Box 6)
- Student Publications
  Student Publications are newsletters produced by students of the School of Nursing, such as The Artery, The Syndrome and The TPR.
  - Newsletters
    - The Artery, 1979-1991, 2 folders (Box 6)
    - The Syndrome, 1972-1977 (Box 6)
    - The TPR
      - volumes 1-10 1936-1947, 2 folders (Box 6)
- Archived School of Nursing Website
  The Archived Website series documents the academic programs, accomplishments, resources, events, and people at the School of Nursing. Content includes important news and announcements, publications (such as newsletters and course catalogs), and information about admissions, curriculum, degree requirements, faculty, and the overall mission of the School. The website series is arranged chronologically, with captures from 2002 and 2003 stored on CD. Starting in 2010, this archived website will be captured on a regular, ongoing basis as part of the University of Michigan Web Archives, hosted at http://webarchives.cdlib.org/a/universityofmichigan/.
  - Website capture May 15, 2002, 1 optical disks CDs (Box 2)
    (Original URL http://www.nursing.umich.edu/)
  - Website as of May 22, 2003, 1 optical disks CDs (Box 3)
  - Archived School of Nursing home page 2010-[ongoing]
  - Archived websites related to the School of Nursing 2010-[ongoing]